I would like to share with you a few thoughts about this question of homosexuality.
Among the homosexuals,
there are people who take the view that what I do is no one's concern,
but it's my private business.
However,
all things which take place in the sexual sphere are not the private affair of the individual,
but signify the life and death of the nation.
The nation that produces a great many children stands to attain world domination.
Another thing.
The homosexual is a person who is categorically mentally ill.
I hope we can continue the work of racial purification that we are currently carrying out for Germany.
Considered weak,
perverted,
degenerate,
homosexuals were vigorously opposed by the Nazi regime,
which sought to prevent the spread of this contagious disease.
While they weren't subjected to mass extermination like Jews,
they were victims of targeted persecution,
a piece of history the general public still knows very little about.
More than 50,000 homosexuals were sentenced to imprisonment.
Between 5,000 to 10,000 were deported to a concentration camp.
Regardless of class,
age,
or ideology,
most of them would lose their lives.
I suffered only due to this reason,
that I loved somebody that I loved a man.
Sometimes I say...
I can forgive the Germans,
but never forget.
Never forget.
It is too difficult to forget.
I never went to Linz again.
My homeland vexes me.
I met two schoolmates once.
So Erwin,
said one of them,
did Hitler not gas you?
Nope,
I said.
I got away from him.
And the other one said,
vermin always comes back home.
I'll just tell you,
coming home can be worse than going away.
Nobody ever asked what I suffered.
They didn't say,
you poor little thing,
or anything like that.
They just regretted having reared something like me.
The persecution of homosexuals by the Nazis took place in a particular historical context.
Since 1871,
so-called unnatural sex had been punishable under the German Criminal Code.
Paragraph 175.
The unnatural fornication that is committed between two persons of the male sex,
or between persons and animals,
is punishable with imprisonment.
Loss of civic rights may also be indicated.
After World War I,
the Weimar Republic that followed the Empire kept paragraph 175,
but was relatively tolerant of homosexuals.
Dozens of specialized publications were published for a male,
female,
and transvestite readership.
They featured articles,
naughty photos,
and even personals.
The country counted more than 1.5 million homosexuals and Berlin was considered the homosexual capital of Europe.
Discretion
remained key.
Homosexuals met up in public gardens,
for example.
In big city centers,
urinals provided readily available intimacy away from prying eyes.
Bathhouses also provided opportunities to meet new people without too much exposure.
While arrests were frequent,
they rarely led to full prison terms.
Usually less than three months.
There
were many places in Berlin nightlife where homosexuals and lesbians could socialize.
Kleist Casino,
Monocle,
Violetta,
Mon Bijou,
Silhouette,
Domino or El Dorado,
made famous by its transvestite shows.
Bars,
dance halls,
cabarets were intellectuals,
artists and bourgeois mingled,
living it up in the roaring
20s.
Foreign tourists also,
or even just curious bystanders.
A motley clientele gathered here to take part in carefree,
transgressive parties,
where everyone was allowed to live out their differences in total freedom.
It wasn't unusual to hear Das Lille Lied,
The Lavender Song,
a bona fide homosexual anthem composed in 1920.
Condemning the country's dramatic economic situation,
strangled by the repayment of war damages,
Adolf Hitler,
by the same token,
promised to make Germany great again and restore order and morality.
The Nazi Party was constantly gaining new members,
and its ideology was spreading to all strata of society.
Accused of being perverted and decadent,
homosexuals were often targeted.
A major thorn in the Nazi's side was Dr.
Magnus Hirschfeld.
An adamant campaigner for the abolition of Paragraph 175,
Hirschfeld was one of the founders,
in 1897,
of the Scientific Humanitarian Committee,
the first homosexual association in history.
In 1919 in central Berlin,
he also created an internationally renowned sexology institute,
a scientific research and documentation center.
He championed the idea that homosexuality was innate,
that a woman's soul was imprisoned in a man's body.
1928,
29,
we went to Dr.
Magda Söschert.
I'll never forget that.
Where we hang our coats,
they're all bricks out of wood around the whole thing,
you know.
I screamed out laughing.
And the guy who was sitting on the desk,
well,
he says,
what are you laughing,
mister?
This is our trademark,
period.
At the Institute,
Hirschfeld welcomed homosexual and transgender patients.
He also organized the first sexual reassignment operations.
A Jew and homosexual himself,
he was physically attacked by the Nazis on several occasions and was the object of numerous smear campaigns.
I remember that in the news they always had caricatures of him.
Look at him,
the new paragraph 175,
making fun of them.
The arrival of the Nazis into power resulted in radical change.
Hitler was named Chancellor on January 30,
1933.
On March 20,
he proclaimed the advent of the Third Reich.
Immediately afterwards,
repressive measures were taken against political opponents and the program to purify Aryan society began.
On May 6th,
1933,
Magnus Hirschfeld's institute was ransacked by a group of Nazi students and members of the SA.
Since he was traveling to France at the time,
the sexologist was safe,
but the books in the library were seized and burned a few days later in Opera Square.
A bust in Hirschfeld's likeness,
carried at the end of a pike,
was set ablaze.
I was born in Berlin,
right?
And I was a
Berliner. But when the Nazis came,
you had the feeling you are a stranger.
All of a sudden.
The hunt for homosexuals began immediately.
Some went into exile.
In February 1933,
activist organizations were dissolved and magazines banned.
A wave of arrests was made,
targeting repeat offenders,
transvestites,
and prostitutes.
Many clubs were closed down,
like the iconic El Dorado,
which was converted into a Nazi party headquarters.
In Columbia House,
a large prison in South Berlin,
homosexuals rubbed shoulders with political prisoners and common criminals.
Many were also sent to the first concentration camps,
opened in 1933,
at Arenenberg,
Lichtenberg and Dachau.
Hitler still had to restructure the military,
which raised the issue of the SA,
the paramilitary organization that accompanied the rise of the Nazi Party.
It was led by Ernst Röhm,
who had been a loyal friend of the Fuhrer and supported him since 1919.
Röhm's ambition then was to become head of the official army.
Heinrich Himmler and Hermann Göring convinced Hitler that a coup was imminent.
At the end of June 1934,
Ernst Röhm and dozens of SA cadres were finally arrested before being executed for high treason.
Röhm's homosexuality,
shared by many of his lieutenants,
was also singled out as further proof of his moral decline.
The Night of the Long Knives would soon have terrible consequences.
for all German homosexuals.
Rome was a gay man.
People knew that.
We read about what happened in the newspapers,
but it was never really established that Rome was actually fomenting rebellion.
And I don't believe it.
They just wanted to get rid of him.
And then nothing happened.
That was from June to October.
To the end of the year,
nothing happened at all.
And then suddenly,
they hunted down all the gay people and locked them up.
I was at my parents'
for Christmas 1934,
and I received a citation for criminal activity.
I never defended myself against it.
Lots of people said,
yes,
I'm gay,
but I didn't do this or that and so on.
I was always so confident.
I just said,
yes,
I lived with him and did this and did that.
I never thought I was harming anybody else.
The message sent to the German population was clear.
All homosexuals were now targets.
Without exception,
between 1934 and 1936,
indictments multiplied by five.
During interrogations,
mental and physical torture was used to make detainees confess to their crime.
I am homosexual by inclination.
For purposes of sexual activity,
I have taken street boys from Alexander Platz.
I have masturbated with them in hallways.
I met five or six boys in total.
To some,
I gave one Reichsmark,
otherwise B or cigarettes.
These were boys who were probably just visiting Berlin for the day.
Informing was officially encouraged.
Colleagues,
neighbors,
acquaintances.
From that point on,
homosexuals had to be wary of everyone.
The press ramped up its homophobic attacks.
The trial of wine merchant Leopold Obermeyer was the subject of a terrible smear campaign.
It also enabled the Nazis to establish a dubious link between Jewishness and homosexuality.
On September 1st,
1935,
Paragraph 175 was amended.
It was no longer only sexual relations that were punished.
A simple embrace,
or even an admission of desire,
could result in a conviction.
In cases of seduction of a minor or prostitution,
the penalty could be increased to 10 years hard labor.
Heinrich Himmler,
head of the SS and all police and security forces,
was certainly homosexuality's biggest enemy.
He was obsessed with hunting them down.
On October 10,
1936,
he created the Central Office for the Combating of Homosexuality and Abortion.
Within the Reich's criminal police,
led by Joseph Messinger,
who was already in charge of such matters at the Gestapo headquarters,
the office now centralized all files on identified cases.
Everywhere in Germany,
the hunt intensified.
In 1935,
there were 2,100 convictions under paragraph 175.
In 1936,
the number reached over 5,000.
In each of the following years,
1937 and 1938,
over 8,000 sentences were handed down.
Considered to be enemies of the state,
homosexuals could even be incarcerated without a trial in a concentration camp.
as a preventative measure.
With the expansion of the Reich and the outbreak of the Second World War,
Nazi policies against homosexuals varied from territory to territory.
In general,
the German Criminal Code only applied to Reich nationals,
Germans,
and inhabitants of annexed territories.
However,
Placed under the direct authority of a high-ranking Nazi,
the Netherlands introduced the equivalent of paragraph 175 in 1940.
The young Tymon Hoffman was informed on and arrested at the age of 16.
A simple address book he was found carrying turned his life upside down.
And then I heard one detective saying to the other,
well,
we're on the right track.
Because this has names in it that we know too.
So you're sitting in your cell,
and out of fear you don't dare do anything.
I spent three days there.
And in those three days I was taken upstairs again and again.
And I believe that on the third day they said,
yeah,
now you'll see your friends and you'll have to identify them.
And you would you had can it But I do not think loss but at the time there wasn't any glass that you could see anyone through
No, you had to walk right up to them now
You wait,
you know then you're in yourself thinking
I betrayed them,
although I didn't betray them,
because I couldn't have betrayed them,
because they were in that stupid notebook.
That's what was so miserable.
In Poland,
the young Stefan Kaczynski was arrested in 1941.
He was prosecuted for having an affair with a Weimar officer.
On 5th December 1942,
the Wachmeister took me to the judgment,
to the judge.
I remember there was only my mother,
no people and me.
And maybe five or six in black dresses,
the judges.
They were shouted and cried.
I have to be isolated.
I am demoralized military,
German military,
me,
Polack,
and how I could do that?
I must be punished.
I must be punished for long time.
And I was 17 years old.
And they stated me,
they punished me for five years.
Exactly Zuchthaus.
Often,
once their prison sentence had been served,
homosexuals were not released.
Many of them were sent to a concentration camp for an indefinite length of time.
The Nazis believed they could still be cured through a therapeutic cocktail of forced labor,
humiliation,
deprivation.
Some of them were sent to Sachsenhausen,
Flossenburg or Neuengam.
Others to Buchenwald,
Auschwitz.
Their uniforms bore a reminder of the infamous reason for their incarceration.
The number 175 or the letter
A.
Arschficker.
Assfucker.
And when the decision was made to identify the different categories of prisoners with colored triangles,
pink was chosen to stigmatize them.
Rudolf Brasda,
who died in 2011,
was the last survivor to have worn the pink triangle in a Nazi concentration camp.
The Czechoslovakian born and living on German soil was arrested in 1937.
He served a six-month sentence,
then was deported to Czechoslovakia,
where he settled in the Sudetenland region.
History quickly caught up with him.
After Sudetenland was annexed,
the German criminal code was applied.
Rudolf,
who had found a new love life,
was convicted again.
14 months of prison before being deported in 1942 to Buchenwald until the end of the war.
Unlike men,
lesbian women were not covered by paragraph 175.
They were morally condemned but tolerated,
provided they remained discreet and avoided cutting their hair too short or wearing masculine outfits,
for example.
And while their sexual practices were never the primary reason for their internment,
they were an exacerbating factor.
Elsa Conrad,
owner of Berlin's famous Mon Bijou Club,
served 15 months in prison before being transferred to the Morrigan camp.
She was arrested for insulting the Reich,
but her police file clearly mentions her homosexuality.
It remains difficult to estimate precisely how many lesbian women were deported.
We know that some of them were sent to Ravensbruck,
the main women's concentration camp north of Berlin.
Mary Punger,
labeled as asocial,
Jewish,
and lesbian,
was imprisoned there from 1940.
Dr.
Friedrich Mennecke,
responsible for the Actean T4 program,
designed to eliminate the physically and mentally handicapped,
finally decided to execute her.
She died in a gas chamber on May 28,
1942.
Two days later,
Henny Sherman,
also Jewish,
shared the same fate.
Dr.
Menneker summarizing his diagnosis behind her ID photo wrote that she was a compulsive lesbian.
Himmler tracked down homosexuals even within the ranks of the SS.
The Reich elite forces which he led could not tolerate the same excesses as the SA.
His instructions were clear.
Naturally,
these people will in all cases be publicly denounced and ostracized and handed over to the courts.
Having served their sentence,
they will,
upon my orders,
be taken to a concentration camp,
and there,
if they attempt to escape,
they will be shot.
In this way,
I hope to get this type of person out of the SS,
down to the last individual.
Whether civilian or military,
German society in its entirety had to meet the requirements of the Aryan ideal.
A society brought to order,
united around its dream of conquest,
the promise of a glorious future,
and carried forward by strong,
disciplined,
and virile men.
The cult of the masculine athletic body was celebrated through sports and nudism.
It also inspired the works of Nazi artists like sculptor
Arno Brecker,
one of the favorites of the Ministry of Propaganda,
and the Führer himself.
An aesthetic that was rather ambiguous,
however,
given its homoerotic undertones.
To instill the Aryan values of discipline,
obedience,
and efficiency,
indoctrination began at an early age.
By 1936,
the Hitler Youth already had over 5 million members.
Enrollment became mandatory starting in 1939.
From then on,
all particularities had to be erased within the group.
Albert Kristol
A young science professor living near Hamburg was a homosexual.
He was also a staunch opponent of National Socialism,
which he publicly criticized.
He was prevented from teaching and arrested several times before being deported to a concentration camp.
First Sachsenhausen,
then Flossenburg,
where he wore the pink triangle until the end of the war.
Unlike Hitler Youth,
several youth movements shared a more open vision of society,
displaying a curiosity for other cultures and tolerance for homosexuality.
Many of their leaders were arrested.
Robert Olbermann,
who founded the Narotherbund organization in the Cologne area with his twin brother,
Karl,
was arrested in 1936 and sentenced.
Under paragraph 175,
after 18 months of forced labor,
he was transferred to the Sachsenhausen camp.
Also a homosexual,
Dr.
Rudi Pallas was head of the Southern Legion Youth Movement in Berlin.
He was also detained in Sachsenhausen in 1937 on the same grounds.
During their incarceration,
Robert Olbermann and Rudi Pallas
Both wore the pink triangle and distinguished themselves by organizing a resistance group that succeeded in uniting homosexual and political deportees.
Olbermann was killed in Dachau in 1941.
As for Rudy Pallas,
who was still being prosecuted for his homosexuality after the war,
he finally committed s****** in 1951.
Me
too.
Sir,
the night usually has deeper peace.
The run?
In Nazi Germany,
Aryan youth was targeted by many campaigns orchestrated by the Ministry of Propaganda.
To encourage marriage,
for example.
Women were above all considered to be future spouses,
for the purpose of procreation.
The country was becoming increasingly militarized.
Hitler set a minimum goal of four children per family.
For the Nazi authorities,
people engaging in homosexuality were depriving Germany of the children they owed the country.
Homosexuals accounted for less than 1%
of the total prisoners sent to the camps.
Yet their life expectancy was among the lowest.
In this dehumanized world,
facing the cruelty and homophobia of the SS,
they had to learn to survive.
The day came for us to be transported to Sachsenhausen in goods wagons.
We were all ordered out of the police car.
And standing there were the SS scoundrels
Knittler, Kaiser and Fickert.
Shepherds on leads,
and people were taken out in alphabetical order.
And everyone got clouded over the head or in the belly.
I got my prisoner number with a pink triangle,
pink meaning whore.
And with that,
I got an order.
There's a rope.
Hang yourself.
Run at the guard towers or walk into the electric fence.
You're never getting out of here.
For fear of homosexuals contaminating other prisoners,
they were often subjected to isolation.
Our block was occupied only by homosexuals.
with about 250 men in each wing.
We could only sleep in our nightshirts.
Had to keep our hands outside the blankets because you queer assholes aren't going to start jerking off here.
We were also forbidden to approach nearer than 5 meters of the other blocks.
Other categories of prisoner were similarly forbidden to enter our block.
My dormitory,
with 180 prisoners or more,
contained the most varied collection of people.
All of these otherwise decent people had been assembled here,
in this melting pot of disgrace and torment.
The queer block of a concentration camp,
for extermination through back-breaking labor,
hunger,
and torture.
An integral part of the so-called re-education program.
Disciplinary commandos,
in which homosexuals were often assigned the most arduous tasks.
We gays were assembled into work detachments of 12 to 15 men,
led by an SS work leader,
a capo,
and a foreman to work in the granite quarry.
This is where the stones were dug and prepared for Hitler's great building projects,
for roadway bridges and the like.
The quarry claimed very many victims,
with the SS and capos often deliberately contributing to the large number of accidents.
When our work detachment returned to camp in the evening,
we had always to wait at the camp gate until we'd been counted.
Whether the returning prisoners were alive or dead was a matter of indifference to the SS.
All that was important was the number.
Within the camp walls,
they also had to protect themselves from r***.
Sexual abuse was common,
and the Pink Triangles,
allegedly perverse and decadent,
became prime targets.
So there was no other choice but to place myself under the protection of a block senior or couple who would fend off other propositions and provide me with additional rations.
In return,
I had to be lover and bed partner at any time when my protector had the desire.
My will to survive the concentration camp was uncommonly strong,
but any such survival against the brutes of the SS had a high price.
The price of morality,
decency,
and honor.
One day,
the first of the German prisoners of war came.
One of them was an officer cadet,
you know,
proper junker,
blonde,
nice uniform,
who works.
It didn't take long for him to come to me.
Walter,
I've heard that the camp senior was giving you trouble.
He's been trying it on with me.
I'm going to the camp HQ to complain.
Leave me out of it.
I knew how it was.
The officers stuck together,
the celebrities,
you know.
I said,
if you say a word about this,
they'll do you in.
And I saw what happened.
He went to camp HQ and complained.
Next thing he's back in camp and they polished him off.
They stuck a hose up his rear end.
turned on the water,
cold water.
That's how they did him in.
Gave him the heaviest work in the quarry.
He got that.
He came back and he said to me,
I can't stand anymore.
If you ever get home,
don't tell my people how I died here.
In some of the camps,
homosexuals also had to submit to a normalization challenge by having sex with women in brothels set up on site.
Most of these female prisoners wore black triangles.
They were considered asocial and had been promised release after six months.
This instruction from the Reich only showed how little the SS leadership and their scientific advisors understood homosexuality.
On three occasions,
I myself had to visit the brothel.
What pleasure was I expected to get when the poor girl lifted her legs and called,
Hurry up
So that she could be finished as soon as possible.
On top of which,
I knew that some SS man would be spying on me through the hole.
In
1940,
following the defeat of the French army,
Hitler decided to annex Alsace and Moselle.
Returned to France in 1919 under the Treaty of Versailles,
these territories once again belonged de facto to the German Reich.
So far spared by French criminal law,
the region's homosexuals were now being hunted down by the police.
From 1942 onwards,
German legislation was officially enforced,
paving the way for their prosecution.
Alsace's special status meant that it hosted the only Nazi concentration camp on French soil,
Struthof,
located at an altitude of 800 meters in the heart of the Vosges Mountains.
Nearly 300 people deported for homosexuality were detained there during the war.
However,
the vast majority of them,
over 90%,
came from Germany.
When not deported to free France,
Alsatians and Moselle residents arrested for homosexuality were generally incarcerated in security camps,
sometimes without a trial.
Just a few kilometers away from Stutthof,
the Vorbruch-Scherbeck safety camp alone held more than a hundred prisoners on homosexuality charges during the war.
Like Joseph Regisseur,
a Strasbourg merchant who was sent to the camp after serving a
30-month sentence in Strasbourg and Germany.
Or Pierre Siel,
a young sales apprentice arrested in 1941 in Malouz.
He was only 17.
In his memoirs,
he describes the terrible conditions of the Volvrukschermek camp.
Insults,
deprivation,
abuse.
He even describes how he watched helplessly as his boyfriend was executed.
Two SS men brought a young man to the center of our square.
Horrified,
I recognized Joe,
my loving friend,
who was only 18 years old.
Then the loudspeakers broadcast some noisy classical music.
while the SS stripped him naked and shoved a tin pail over his head.
Next,
they sicced their ferocious German shepherds on him.
The guard dogs first
First bit into his groin and thighs,
then devoured him right in front of us.
I will never forget that barbaric murder of my love.
After six months,
Pierre Seal was summoned to the camp commander's office.
Just as he feared the worst,
he was surprised to learn he was being released on good behavior.
I could now become a full-fledged German citizen.
I would even be permitted to say Heil Hitler when leaving his office,
a privilege reserved for well-behaved men in the Reich.
But this freedom would be short-lived.
Like other Alsatian malgré nous,
Pierre Siel was soon forcibly conscripted into the Wehrmacht and sent to the front in Yugoslavia and Russia.
So it was off to war at 18 and a half,
and in a German uniform.
The horrors I had already seen and suffered in the concentration camp would be inflicted on me throughout Europe.
For three years,
I became a ghost in the service of death.
Among other Alsatian homosexuals who were victims of Nazi repression,
Robert Stelter,
a vineyard worker.
After a stint in Vorburg-Schirmeck,
he was deported to Struthof,
then Buchenwald,
and finally Dora,
where he met his death.
Albert B.,
a chemist from Strasbourg,
served a two-year sentence in Alsace and various German prisons.
Jean Oswald,
another young laborer from Mulhouse,
died at Struthof in June 1944.
In the rest of France,
around a hundred people were persecuted because of their homosexuality.
In occupied France,
the Nazis had little concern for these decadents,
who they felt were helping to weaken the rest of the population.
The few cases recorded mainly concerned men suspected of having slept with German soldiers.
Lucien P.
was a singer in Parisian cabarets such as Monaco,
Loublanc and Pigalle's.
He was part of a threesome with John T.,
a clothing store salesman,
and Karl Schwerbel,
an SS official.
In 1941,
all three men are arrested.
Schwerbel was sent back to Germany and incarcerated in Sachsenhausen.
The two Frenchmen were incarcerated for over two years in the Paris region,
before finally being deported to the Buchenwald camp.
While shooting the film Mermoz,
homosexual actor Robert Hugues Lambert was caught in a raid in a Parisian café in 1943.
He was accused of idleness and said to have had an affair with a German officer.
He too was deported.
and died in Flossenburg at the age of 36.
To protect minors,
the Vichy regime passed a discriminatory law in 1942,
setting the age of sexual majority at 21 for homosexual men and women,
compared with 13 for heterosexuals.
However,
this law seems to have had limited impact.
On the other hand,
Starting in 1940,
many homosexuals were arrested in the name of moral order.
In the end,
at least 40 of them were subjected to administrative internment in supervised residence camps in unoccupied zones.
At Fort Barreau in the Isère department,
or the Citadel of Cisteron in the Basse-Alpes region,
most have criminal records.
prostitutes,
petty criminals,
and rubbed shoulders with political opponents and delinquents of all kinds.
Henry Pasca,
known as Fleur de Thé from Nice,
was 20 years old,
with no known occupation,
and was well known to the police.
He was detained in Cisterone in 1940,
Fort Barreau two years later,
and then deported to Buchenwald in 1944.
In the concentration camps,
homosexual prisoners were often used as guinea pigs for experiments on diphtheria,
typhoid fever,
or malaria.
Castrations were also sometimes performed.
Karl-Heinz Rodenberg,
neurologist,
psychiatrist,
and scientific director of the Reich Central Office for the Combating of Homosexuality and Abortion,
claimed that forced castration was the surest way to protect society from the urges of homosexuals.
Starting in 1939,
voluntary castration was sometimes offered to homosexual inmates in return for the promise of a hypothetical release.
Himmler now stipulated that any homosexual who consented to castration and whose conduct was good would shortly be released from concentration camp.
Many of the Pink Triangle prisoners actually believed Himmler's promises and consented to castration with a view to escaping their murderous persecutions.
But when they were released,
this was only to be sent to the SS Dürrlewanger Penal Division on the Russian front to be butchered in the partisan war and die a hero's death for Hitler and Himmler.
In 1944,
Danish endocrinologist Carl Vernet was integrated into the SS.
to conduct an experimental sexual polarity reversal program.
He convinced Himmler that it was possible to cure homosexuals with an artificial gland implant.
By releasing male hormones into their bodies,
it would modify their sexual orientation.
At the end of the year,
experiments were conducted for several weeks at the camp in Buchenwald.
The artificial gland effects were then thoroughly analyzed on about 15 patients between the ages of 23 and 55.
For
the German homosexuals who survived the Nazi atrocities,
The end of the war and release from the camps did not mean the end of their torments.
Paragraph 175 wasn't abolished,
and male homosexuality continued to be considered a crime.
They were often denied the status of Nazi victims,
as was the case with artist Richard Gruner,
a survivor of Sachsenhausen and Flossenburg,
who in 1946 produced an album of lithographs documenting the horrors of the camps.
Many of them were sent to prison again.
Arrested in 1938,
imprisoned in Neuengam and then Auschwitz,
and Mauthausen,
Nurse Karl Gorath was re-arrested in 1947.
He faced the same judge as under the Nazis and was re-sentenced to five years.
As for the former torturers of homosexuals,
their post-war fates varied.
Taken prisoner by the Allies,
Heinrich Himmler committed s****** on May 22nd,
1945.
Joseph Messinger,
who was in charge of the Reich Central Office for the Combating of Homosexuality and Abortion upon its creation,
was finally convicted in Poland for his role in the destruction of the Warsaw Ghetto and hanged on March 7,
1947.
On the other hand,
no charges were brought against Dr.
Rodenberg,
a major player in the sterilization and castration programs.
He continued to practice medicine in Germany.
and died in 1995 at the age of 91.
As for Carl Vernet,
he always denied having experimented with his artificial gland on Buchenwald inmates.
After registering the patent and attempting to market it to pharmaceutical companies,
he finally fled to Argentina in 1946,
where he died 20 years later.
For several decades,
Nazi persecution of homosexuals remained a taboo topic,
forgotten by officials.
In the history,
most victims continue to keep silent about their experiences.
Austrian Joseph Coutt was the first to tell the story for the general public.
Men with the Pink Triangle,
published in 1972 under the pseudonym of Heinz Heger,
describes the six years he spent in the camps and how difficult it was to find his place in society after the war.
In the early days after my homecoming,
the neighbors made a bit of a fuss about this queer concentration camp returnee.
And what had I done to be sent off this way?
What infamous crime or damage to the community?
What does it say about the world we live in if an adult man is told how and whom he should love?
Homosexuality was finally decriminalized in East Germany in 1968.
and in West Germany the following year.
However,
it wasn't until 1994 that paragraph 175 disappeared from the criminal code altogether.
In the early
1970s, thanks to LGBT associations,
Remembrance work finally began.
The story of the homosexual victims of Nazism was featured in articles,
debates,
Survivor accounts were collected.
Finally,
on May 17th,
2002,
the Bundestag voted for their rehabilitation.
And in 2008,
the memorial dedicated to them in the heart of Berlin soberly but forcefully affirms the right of gays and lesbians from now on to love as they choose.
Sometimes from time there are so very heavy thoughts.
Even now,
me,
I am
71. Who knows,
maybe tomorrow,
after tomorrow I'll die and there will be no documentation.
It must be for the young people.
You see,
as I told you,
I cannot,
I can forgive,
but not forget.
Especially for the young.
They must know how it was.
difficult in the war and what for for the kind reason only the war that i like at men